Finding Aid for Lyman E. Cooley Papers, 1865-1917
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lyman E. Cooley papers 1865-1917
Cooley, Lyman Edgar, 1850-1917.
4 linear ft.
Chicago, Illinois engineer, editor The American Engineer, member of the International Deep Waterways Commission. Professional correspondence relating to the Chicago Drainage Canal, the St. Lawrence Waterway, the Lakes-to-the-Gulf Deep Waterway Association, the controversy over the location of an isthmian canal between the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans, 1897-1898, and other public works consulting projects.
851003 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the Graduate Library of the University of Michigan (donor no. 1278 )
The collection is open for research.
Lyman Edgar Cooley was one of Chicago's best-known consulting hydraulic engineers. After graduating from Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, he taught engineering subjects at Northwestern University (1874-1877). He next worked as assistant engineer on the construction of a bridge over the Missouri River. From 1879 to 1884, he served as assistant engineer on the Mississippi and Missouri river improvements. In September 1884, he began a year's work as editor of The American Engineer. After this period he devoted himself to the engineering features of waterway problems. He achieved prominence in promoting the undertaking of the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal becoming first chief engineer of the project. He was later elected one of the trustees of the Chicago District. According to one source, Cooley gave form to the solution of the problems pertaining to the Chicago Sanitary Canal, its relations to lakes and rivers, and its sanitary and constructive features.
In 1895, President Cleveland appointed Cooley to be a member of the International Commission to make investigations for a ship canal between the Great Lakes and the Atlantic Ocean. He was knowledgeable about deep-water navigation of the Great Lakes and became consulting engineer for the Lakes-to-the-Gulf Deep Waterway Association. He was also interested in the Isthmian Canal problem, visiting Panama and Nicaragua as consulting engineer with the contractors' and engineers' expedition. He died February 3, 1917.
The Lyman Cooley papers reflect his interest in the Chicago Drainage Canal, the St. Lawrence Waterway, the Lakes to the Gulf Waterway, the Nicaragua vs. Panama Isthmian Canal controversy, and public works in the period 1880-1915. Comprised mainly of correspondence, the collection does include a few miscellaneous notes and reports.
Subjects:
The American engineer.; Engineers--Illinois--Chicago.; Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); International Deep Waterways Commission.; Panama Canal (Panama); Saint Lawrence Seaway.; Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal (Ill.); Water-power.
Contributors:
Altgeld, John Peter, 1847-1902.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Cullom, Shelby Moore, 1829-1914.; Lorimer, William, 1861-1934.; Madden, Martin Barnaby, 1855-1928.; Morgan, John Tyler, 1824-1907.; Waddell, J. A. L. (John Alexander Low), 1854-1938
- Correspondence
  The correspondence is mostly of a business nature, although there are a great many love letters from Lucy MacMillan, later Mrs. Lyman Cooley, written in the early 1870's and a few letters from his children. Aside from the many engineers who wrote to him in 1884-1885, when he was editor of The American Engineer. his correspondence includes letters from J.A.L. Waddell in 1885, April 5, 1885, June 24, 1885, Nov. 20, 1885 describing conditions in Japan where he was engineering professor at a Japanese University. Other correspondents include: Edward Cragin, Oct. and Nov. 1897; Frank Flower, 1895; C. S. Harrison, Isthmian Canal Commissioner and later associated with the Denver Water Union (throughout), Senator John T. Morgan (Illinois), March 25 and Sept. 25, 1905; Rep. John Corliss (Michigan), January 16, 1899; William Lorimer, U.S. Representative and Senator from Illinois, 1909-1910; Senator Shelby M. Cullom (Illinois) Dec. 1895, Feb. 1895 (2 letters), July 1897; Rep. Martin B. Madden (Illinois),1914-1915; Judge John P. Altgeld (later governor), March 16, 1891, Mortimer E. Cooley, 1884-1895 and 1914-1916, Harry B. Hutchins, May 27, 1916; James B. Angell, 1895-1898. Angell along with Cooley and John F. Russell was a member of the International Deep Waterways Commission.
  - Undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1865-1873, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1874 andca. 1871-1874 from Lucena MacMillan (Box 1)
  - 1882-July 1895, 52 folders (Box 1)
  - August 1895-1909, 54 folders (Box 2)
  - 1910-January 1917, 49 folders (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Professional Papers
  In addition to correspondence, there are miscellaneous notes and reports and one bound notebook, including genealogical material, receipts, accounts, and engineering reports. These reports are concerned with such projects as the Sanitary District of Chicago, public works project, Huron River waterpower in Michigan, flood control in Saginaw and in Grand Rapids, Denver Water Union and Lake Cheesman, Erie Barge Canal, and Great Lakes to the Gulf Deep Waterways. Also included are such things as notes for speeches and some compositions written in the 1860's while a student at Canandaigua Academy.
  - Digest of Testimony, Marseilles Land and Water Power Co. vs. Northern Illinois Light and Traction Co., ca. 1913, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Marseille (Illinois) Hydro-Electric Test, 1913 (Box 3)
  - Report: "Wire Netting as a Means of Improving the Mississippi River," 1881 (Box 3)
  - Notebook containing notes for engineering papers, undated (Box 4)
  - Huron River waterpower reports, 1904 (Box 4)
  - Appraisal of the Omaha waterworks, 1904 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Engineering reports (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Biographical and genealogical material (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea (Box 4)